<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Text Analysis Overview on ATAP</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/</link><description>Recent content in Text Analysis Overview on ATAP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:23:12 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Research Objects</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/research-objects/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:23:12 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/research-objects/</guid><description>The ATAP workbench will enable researchers to work in ways which improve the reproducibility and accountability of their research. To do this, the output of your work in ATAP will be a fully documented research object.
Research objects are a single package that collects the data, code and other resources used in a piece of research and allows it to be a cite-able research output in its own right. At the end of your work in ATAP, there will be the automated option to package together the components of your workflow, such as:</description></item><item><title>Text Analysis Overview</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/overview/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:23:12 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/overview/</guid><description>Understanding Text as Data Many definitions of data include an element such as individual items of information. If we consider text to include any sort of language in use, covering different modalities (spoken, written signed) and different extents (from individual sounds to multi-volume books), then fitting text to this definition requires some abstraction. We have to define some unit or units of analysis and we can then treat each of those units as an individual item of information.</description></item><item><title>Preparing Text Data</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/data-prep/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/data-prep/</guid><description>Introducing data preparation concepts This graphic is, sadly, all too true. Data scientists and those who are using data as part of their research spend much of their time preparing their dataset and transforming its structure into a format that can be used (often referred to as data wrangling or data munging). The Australian Text Analytics Platform will offer a range of tools to assist in cleaning text data and performing other preliminary operations which can prepare the data for analysis.</description></item><item><title>Useful Methods</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/methods/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 16:46:42 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/text-analysis/methods/</guid><description>Counting words More complex methods - Classification More complex methods - Others Visualisation
Introduction Throughout this page, we have given links to further information in Wikipedia and in the tutorials provided by the Language Technology and Data Analysis Laboratory LADAL at The University of Queensland. We also have given references to published research using the methods we discuss.
LADAL has an overview of text analysis and distant reading.
Counting Words Word frequency Knowing how frequently words occur in a text can already give us information about that text and frequency lists based on large corpora are a useful tool in themselves - you can download such lists for the (original) British National Corpus.</description></item></channel></rss>