<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ATAP</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/</link><description>Recent content on ATAP</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.atap.edu.au/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Events</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</guid><description>Forthcoming workshops Previous workshops Webinars Office Hours
Forthcoming workshops Workshop on Data Migration Skills The Language Data Commons of Australia infrastructure is based on widely-accepted standards such as Research Object Crates (RO-Crate) and the Oxford Common File Layout (OCFL). The project has been running for almost two years and the processes and tools for aligning data with these standards are now well-developed. This workshop aims to show the application of those tools to data in a variety of formats to efficiently migrate material to the LDaCA standards.</description></item><item><title>Previous Workshops</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</guid><description>If your university or organisation would like to host a workshop, please contact us.
Workshop on Language Corpora in Australia Over decades of work in Australia, significant collections of language data have been amassed, including of varieties of Australian English, Australian migrant languages, Australian Indigenous languages, sign languages and others. These collections represent a trove of knowledge not only of language in Australia, but also of Australia’s social and cultural history.</description></item></channel></rss>