<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ATAP</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/</link><description>Recent content on ATAP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.atap.edu.au/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Events</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</guid><description>Webinars Forthcoming workshops Previous workshops Office Hours
Webinars Our webinar series is a joint initiative with the Language Technology and Data Analysis Laboratory (LADAL), (School of Languages and Cultures, University of Queensland). LADAL sponsored webinars take place in the alternate months.
All webinars take place at 8:00PM Brisbane time which is UTC+10. Zoom links will be available one week prior to the event.
October 3 2022 - Paweł Kamocki: European Union Data Protection initiatives and their consequences for research Abstract: The European Union, with its large population and GDP, is a leading force in regulatory globalisation.</description></item><item><title>Previous Workshops</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</guid><description>If your university or organisation would like to host a workshop, please contact us.
Australian Text Analytics Platform tools: Discursis, Juxtorpus, Quotation tool and Semantic tagger This workshop was part of the USyd Digital Humanities Day 2023.
The workshop demonstrated and taught several recently or soon-to-be-released tools from the ATAP text analytic tool collection. These tools include Discursis for analysing human conversational texts, Juxtorpus for advanced corpus slicing and comparison, Semantic Tagger for semantically tagging every word in your text collections, and Quotation Tool for NLP algorithm-based quotation extraction, analysis, and visualisation.</description></item></channel></rss>