<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ATAP</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/</link><description>Recent content on ATAP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.atap.edu.au/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Events</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</guid><description>Forthcoming workshops Previous workshops Webinars Office Hours
Forthcoming workshops Australian Text Analytics Platform: New tools for text analysis The main means of delivery for ATAP is Jupyter notebooks and this half-day workshop will begin with a brief introduction to notebooks for participants not already familiar with the technology. The main body of the workshop will introduce two tools made available by ATAP, and the session will end with a short summary of other tools being developed in recent work.</description></item><item><title>Previous Workshops</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</guid><description>If your university or organisation would like to host a workshop, please contact us.
Exploring Digital Text Collections with Juxtorpus: A Taster Webinar on the Latest ATAP Text Analysis Tool Join us for a hybrid taster webinar on the latest addition to the suite of ATAP text analysis tools - Juxtorpus. Developed to provide a unified framework for managing and exploring text contents and metadata, Juxtorpus offers a Corpus package that enables flexible building, exploration, and slicing of your corpus while maintaining its shape, and a Jux package that allows for easy comparison and highlighting of differences between any two corpora with tools and visualisations that come off-the-shelf.</description></item></channel></rss>