<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ATAP</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/</link><description>Recent content on ATAP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.atap.edu.au/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Events</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/events/</guid><description>Webinars Forthcoming workshops Previous workshops Office Hours
Webinars Our webinar series is a joint initiative with the Language Technology and Data Analysis Laboratory (LADAL), (School of Languages and Cultures, University of Queensland). LADAL sponsored webinars take place in the alternate months.
All webinars take place at 8:00PM Brisbane time which is UTC+10. Zoom links will be available one week prior to the event.
October 3 2022 - Paweł Kamocki: European Union Data Protection initiatives and their consequences for research Abstract: The European Union, with its large population and GDP, is a leading force in regulatory globalisation.</description></item><item><title>Previous Workshops</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 17:13:28 +1000</pubDate><author>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/events/previous/</guid><description>If your university or organisation would like to host a workshop, please contact us.
Jefferson Transcript Search Tool The Search Tool project uses programming to explore how to easily search and manipulate transcripts without the need to &amp;lsquo;clean&amp;rsquo; the transcript. A browser-based tool has been developed, designed to be used by researchers unfamiliar with programming.
The workshop was presented by Evelyn Ansell and is an outcome of her Career Development placement with Australia&amp;rsquo;s Academic and Research Network (AARNET).</description></item></channel></rss>