<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Text Analysis - Tag - ATAP</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/tags/text-analysis/</link><description>Text Analysis - Tag - ATAP</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</managingEditor><webMaster>info@atap.edu.au (Australian Text Analytics Project)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 16:20:35 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.atap.edu.au/tags/text-analysis/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Textbooks, tutorials and tool chests: different ways to learn from notebooks - Part 1</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/posts/notebooks-1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 16:20:35 +1000</pubDate><author>Joel Nothman</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/posts/notebooks-1/</guid><description><![CDATA[<h5 id="this-work-was-supported-by-the-sydney-informatics-hubhttpswwwsydneyeduauresearchfacilitiessydney-informatics-hubhtml-a-core-research-facility-of-the-university-of-sydney">This work was supported by the <a href="https://www.sydney.edu.au/research/facilities/sydney-informatics-hub.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Sydney Informatics Hub</a>, a Core Research Facility of the University of Sydney</h5>
<p>One objective of the Australian Text Analytics Platform is to provide a library of code notebooks that our users – those interested in applying text analytics to research – can learn from and build upon. As the curators of such a resource, we need to learn from what’s been created before for a similar audience; and we need to understand how collections of notebooks can be used as an accessible resource for teaching, critiquing, and creating research using text analytics. These posts therefore summarise the insights we gained from a preliminary survey of key notebook resources.</p>
<p>This first part provides an introductory overview of the use of notebooks in text analytics and examines the pedagogically focussed genres of textbooks and tutorials. The second part looks at two other genres, tool chests and research articles, and ends with a summary and a consideration of how the discussion can inform the design of ATAP.</p>
<h2 id="what-are-notebooks">What are notebooks?</h2>
<p>Notebooks as popularised by the <a href="https://jupyter.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Jupyter project</a> have become a key medium for experimentation and presentation in research and development. They mix code with narrative text, as well as tables, figures and interactive tools generated by the code.</p>
<data id="id-1" data-raw></data>
<p>Figure 1 shows part of a notebook with some text, a code cell and the results generated by running the code</p>
<p>A notebook can be played with interactively, allowing a user to interrogate and tweak the analysis and datasets under construction; but it can also be run as a prefabricated script that fetches a dataset, applies some processing, or generates a report. For researchers, published notebooks provide an opportunity for experimental reproducibility and reusable research pipelines.</p>
<p>Notebooks collected together become a library of tutorials, tools, or reproducible research publications. We found several such collections covering applied text analytics, primarily targeting humanities and social sciences (HASS) researchers, as well as some resources that mix code and narrative, but in which the code cannot be executed directly. To make full use of such resources, it is necessary to copy the code and paste it into a console or another environment where it can be run.</p>
<p>In addition to having a mix of content, and different approaches to teaching or guiding readers to use text analytics tools, we noted a few broad genres of notebook and types of collection, such as tutorials, tool(kits), apps and research experiments, In this post, we focus on tutorials; the following post will look at the remaining genres..
Before going on, we’d like to note that our survey is by no means complete. We’ve not had time to look in detail at the full diversity of relevant notebook collections, but hope that we have captured useful insights about the state of the art.</p>
<h2 id="courses-for-different-horses">Courses for different horses</h2>
<p>While the various resources all covered core applied text analytics concepts – including acquiring data from various sources, analysing n-gram frequencies, extracting named entities, building and evaluating a topic model, and so on – notebook resources reflected different genres and hence user needs. Some sought to present a rigorous curriculum constructed of tutorials or lessons, others treat collections of notebooks as tools for the user to employ in their work, and others demonstrate the use of a notebook as a single-purpose reproducible research article.</p>
<h3 id="courses-and-textbooks">Courses and Textbooks</h3>
<p>The vast majority of notebook collections we identified positioned themselves as courses, with each notebook corresponding to a tutorial. Some tutorials provide scaffolding for exercises (with or without solutions), but at a baseline, they guide readers/users through the use of a tool or concept. Frequently, the intention is for these tutorial notebooks to be walked through in a workshop, but being openly published as notebooks allows users to execute and play with them outside of the classroom.</p>
<p><data id="id-2" data-raw></data>
Tutorials from different authors vary in how much they surround their code with narrative and background explanations of the techniques they are applying. Sinclair and Rockwell’s <a href="https://github.com/sgsinclair/alta/blob/master/ipynb/ArtOfLiteraryTextAnalysis.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">The Art of Literary Text Analysis</a> (ALTA) provides extensive narrative and appears more like a textbook than a course, not intended for delivery, but for learning and reference. Melanie Walsh’s <a href="https://melaniewalsh.github.io/Intro-Cultural-Analytics/05-Text-Analysis/04-Sentiment-Analysis.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Introduction to Cultural Analytics &amp; Python</a> explicitly presents itself as a text book constituted of notebooks, relying on the <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/intro.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Jupyterbook</a> tool to give a glossy, accessible presentation, while also supporting the user to interact with the notebooks. Not unlike ALTA, this course demonstrates a deep appreciation of the breadth of technologies available and how they might be applied – and where they might not be applicable or reliable – in digital humanities contexts. It often supports the learner by giving multiple examples of how to apply a technique, which incidentally means repeated opportunities to demonstrate data preparation with diverse inputs.</p>
<p>For the R programming community, Martin Schweinberger’s <a href="https://slcladal.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">LADAL</a> shows a thoroughness in developing users’ abilities from statistical basics to a breadth of NLP, corpus and computational linguistic methods. (As part of the ATAP project, LADAL tutorials are undergoing conversion from R markdown to Jupyter notebooks.) Technique-oriented introductory tutorials are then complemented with “focus studies” on disciplines of linguistic analysis such as learner language, stylistics or linguistic typology.
In comparison to the above sites, several other tutorial resources are much more bare, simply demonstrating how to implement a technique with little use of discussion or repeated examples.
The varying levels of narrative, and how they present the code, suggests that authors have a mix of goals that we might query:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is the tutorial introducing a technique, or rather its use through code?</li>
<li>Is it teaching the application of a technique, or how it works?</li>
<li>Does it aim to teach the reader how to read the code? How to experiment with the code? How to compose that code themselves?</li>
<li>Does the notebook itself facilitate those engagements with code, or does the more ephemeral teacher?</li>
</ul>
<p>Although not recently updated, we are indebted to Quinn Dombrowski’s curation of a <a href="https://github.com/quinnanya/dh-jupyter#course-materials" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">list of relevant courses and tutorials</a>, among other digital humanities notebooks. A recent player in this space is <a href="https://labs.jstor.org/tapi/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">TAPI (Text Analysis Pedagogy Institute)</a>, which places open publication of notebook-based courses at the core of their researcher schooling. TAPI incorporates several courses by individual presenters, although there does not currently appear to be a high level of standardisation among the TAPI courses, including in their licensing.
<a href="https://programminghistorian.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">The Programming Historian</a> is also an excellent resource for peer-reviewed digital humanities tutorials, often helpfully grounded in use cases. Not being notebooks (nor R markdown), its tutorials can’t be directly executed, leaving the user to copy-paste its code or not engage interactively with its content. What sets the Programming Historian apart is its design as a journal of tutorials, i.e. a collaborative enterprise in text analytics pedagogy. While resources we surveyed are all essentially open to third party contributors who may offer amendments, most collections of tutorial notebooks have single or few authors and are not designed as primarily collaborative endeavours.</p>
<p><a href="/posts/notebooks-2" rel="">Part 2</a> of this post looks at the remaining genres we have identified, libraries and tool chests and presentations of research results. Part 2 also includes a discussion of how the information collected here might shape our view of what ATAP can be.</p>
<p>Note 1: Unfortunately, we confined our survey to English-language resources; and with a focus on the Notebook medium, our analysis is biassed to (but not exclusively) the Python programming language.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Textbooks, tutorials and tool chests: different ways to learn from notebooks - Part 2</title><link>https://www.atap.edu.au/posts/notebooks-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 16:20:35 +1000</pubDate><author>Joel Nothman</author><guid>https://www.atap.edu.au/posts/notebooks-2/</guid><description><![CDATA[<h3 id="more-genres-of-notebooks-and-what-it-all-means-for-atap">More genres of notebooks and what it all means for ATAP</h3>
<h5 id="this-work-was-supported-by-the-sydney-informatics-hubhttpswwwsydneyeduauresearchfacilitiessydney-informatics-hubhtml-a-core-research-facility-of-the-university-of-sydney">This work was supported by the <a href="https://www.sydney.edu.au/research/facilities/sydney-informatics-hub.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Sydney Informatics Hub</a>, a Core Research Facility of the University of Sydney</h5>
<p><a href="/posts/notebooks-1" rel="">Part 1</a> of this post introduced notebooks in general and identified various broad genres of notebook which have been used in providing text analytic tools. That part looked at notebooks as tutorials and the grouping of such materials into courses or textbooks. In this part, we look at notebooks which introduce individual tools and notebooks which present research results. The post ends with a consideration of how our analysis of different genres of notebook might influence the design of ATAP.</p>
<h3 id="libraries-and-tool-chests">Libraries and tool chests</h3>
<p>A “course” comes with a sense of order and completeness; a “tutorial” with a sense of guidance and demonstration. Some notebook collections appear more designed for reference or application than teaching, as if each notebook was a tool you could take from a chest and utilise for your needs.</p>
<p><data id="id-1" data-raw></data>
A notable collection in this space is Tim Sherratt’s <a href="https://glam-workbench.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">GLAM Workbench</a>. Tim often titles a directory of notebooks as “tools, tips and examples”, which nicely summarises the mix of content that users can retrieve from the Workbench. “Tools” might include a <a href="https://nbviewer.org/github/GLAM-Workbench/australian-commonwealth-hansard/blob/master/Harvesting-Commonwealth-Hansard.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">notebook for acquiring Australian parliament’s Hansard transcripts</a>, offering parameters that the user might change for their own project; or an <a href="https://github.com/GLAM-Workbench/trove-newspapers/blob/master/querypic.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">app that summarises query results</a> from the National Library of Australia’s <a href="https://trove.nla.gov.au/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Trove</a>. An app, here, is distinguished by providing interactive widgets within a notebook, rather than expecting the user to set parameters in code and hit “run”. “Examples” includes a <a href="https://nbviewer.org/github/GLAM-Workbench/ozglam-workbench-naa-wap/blob/master/RecordSearch/2.%20Analyse%20a%20series.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">case study</a> of filtering a corpus by its metadata, while a <a href="https://github.com/GLAM-Workbench/trove-newspapers/blob/master/find-non-english-newspapers.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">walkthrough on language detection</a> applied to Trove incorporates many “tips” which help to identify the author’s thinking as his code takes each turn. Case studies like these lie on a spectrum between the genericity of tutorials often applied to demonstration or toy data, and the hypothesis-driven specificity of a research article. Grounding a topic in research use cases may help to evoke a sense of relevance to the user.
<data id="id-2" data-raw></data>
Notebooks presented as reusable tools may also be very similar to tutorials. Until recently, Ithaka’s <a href="https://constellate.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Constellate.org</a> – a core part of TAPI – included tutorial notebooks, and corresponding editions of the same notebook “for research”. (Here’s a <a href="https://github.com/ithaka/tdm-notebooks/blob/ea3c48e0094303a7d40dec4890c6cfdca275d22b/finding-significant-terms.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">tutorial</a> and <a href="https://github.com/ithaka/tdm-notebooks/blob/ea3c48e0094303a7d40dec4890c6cfdca275d22b/finding-significant-terms-for-research.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">research</a> pair on finding key terms in a corpus.) Each “research” notebook omits some of the guidance included in the tutorial, and was rather intended to be applied to a user-supplied dataset. The removal of these applied notebooks notwithstanding, it appears that the Constellate tutorials should dually function as reusable tools. The Constellate platform allows the user to create a corpus from JSTOR content, and select a tutorial/tool notebook from their collection, which is then applied to the new corpus. An important usability feature of reusable tools, and tutorials with this capability, is how they guide or support the user to apply the notebook to their own data.</p>
<p>Although targeting experienced corporate data scientists, rather than HASS researchers, data infrastructure provider Databricks openly publishes another relevant tool chest of notebooks (albeit not designed for the Jupyter platform). Their <a href="https://databricks.com/solutions/accelerators" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Solution Accelerators</a> are designed to support a fairly code-savvy analyst in tackling standard data science problems in industry. (Read “Solution Accelerator” as a less patronising, more businessy, revamp of the term “starter kit”.) A Solution Accelerator notebook mixes narrative and code, inviting the user to bring their own data. It may give them data transformation code, models to apply, questions to ask, and diagnostics to perform. The library of Solution Accelerators shows how even a capable user may appreciate a notebook as a launchpad when working with new techniques. The apparent value of Solution Accelerators to Databricks customers highlights the risk and cost of undertaking analysis without workflow guidance from a notebook.</p>
<p>Unlike tutorials, a notebook tool chest does not make great efforts to build up a user’s skills from scratch, but supports them in selecting a tool that might be appropriate, seeing its relevance, and applying it to their needs.</p>
<h3 id="journals-and-anthologies">Journals and Anthologies</h3>
<p>Through their mix of code, narrative and generated tables and figures, notebooks are a powerful tool for presenting reproducible experimental results. A research paper implemented as a notebook may be rebuilt from its code, reproducing tables, figures and examples as the researcher modifies it. An article-as-notebook is distinguished by its focus on a specific research question, and application of whichever tools are appropriate to draw reliable conclusions. Although individual humanities researchers using digital methods might publish their research as code notebooks (see Quinn Dombrowski’s <a href="https://github.com/quinnanya/dh-jupyter#research--projects" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">list</a> for instance), institutional or discipline-specific collections of research notebooks are not yet common in applied text analysis and HASS. For comparison, a move towards reproducibility in other sciences allows one to find a multitude of research notebooks in venues like <a href="https://paperswithcode.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">paperswithcode.com</a> and <a href="https://codeocean.com/explore/capsules" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Code Ocean</a>.
<data id="id-3" data-raw></data>
When driven by a research question, the notebook author is less interested in demonstrating what techniques are <em>available</em> to apply, and more selective in using techniques that may helpfully harness their data towards a specific goal or narrative. The research thesis thus provides a way to specifically evaluate the output of an analysis: does it support a hypothesis? does it induce a new hypothesis? does it suggest problems in the modelling? The final research notebook may hide aspects of this iterative experimentation, evaluation, and the response of further investigation, issue mitigation, or discarding a path of investigation. (The ideal reproducible research notebook would keep track of dead ends too!)
Tutorials and tools may emulate these processes of iterative development, or provide a range of possible pathways for analysis; the research notebook, however, must keep its focus on the thesis being explored.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://journalofdigitalhistory.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Journal of Digital History</a> is a new player in this space, releasing its first issue in October 2021. This project of the Luxembourg Centre for Contemporary and Digital History and De Gruyter ensures some reproducibility by requiring the code which constructs the research article to be executable and its data available to reproduce tables and figures, while allowing the reader to evaluate and reuse the research implementation. It goes further in harnessing the notebook medium to add layers of depth to peer-reviewed publications in digital history: viewing a JDH publication, a reader is able to hide what they call the “hermeneutic layer” of the work, which provides methodological detail, as distinct from the narrative arc of the research. The notebook medium applied in this way is able to shift several paradigms about how research is constructed, presented, and accessed.</p>
<h3 id="bringing-it-back-to-users">Bringing it back to users</h3>
<p>In positioning the Australian Text Analytics Platform’s role amidst ongoing and past resource creation, we have to consider how our library of notebooks might build outcomes for our users. Here are some outcomes we are considering.</p>
<h4 id="reference-and-application">Reference and Application</h4>
<ul>
<li>User has access to starters’ kits for a wide range of techniques, covering data modelling, validation and analysis, archiving, etc.</li>
<li>User can experiment with standard tools applied to demo data or their own.</li>
<li>User can adapt code notebooks to their own use cases.</li>
<li>User is able to compare alternative methods for similar goals.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="growth-and-learning">Growth and Learning</h4>
<ul>
<li>User is familiar with what selected research methods look like as code.</li>
<li>User is familiar with what end-to-end research looks like as code.</li>
<li>User can prepare their own data for existing or standard tools.</li>
<li>User understands how their research problem might translate to a computational problem, and the applicable techniques.</li>
<li>User is able to combine multiple techniques to achieve their research goals.</li>
<li>User understands how to build good research software.</li>
<li>User can confidently build a notebook from scratch for their own research.</li>
</ul>
<p>We also need to define who our user personas are: is it someone with academic expertise, but little in code? or someone with moderate code literacy, but stuck with how to create notebooks for reproducible research? The latter might be more interested in published starter kits, case studies and experiments, while the former needs the guidance provided by a tutorial.</p>
<h3 id="where-to-from-here">Where to from here?</h3>
<p>By surveying several collections of notebooks for text analytics, we have a stronger understanding of the spectrum of materials ATAP’s library can incorporate, both in content and in genre.</p>
<p>One apparent opportunity is to curate or improve a catalogue of existing resources that will meet the needs of the Australian text analytics research community. It’s also possible to see areas where existing resources may fail to meet the needs of current users of desktop and web tools for corpus analysis from <a href="https://voyant-tools.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Voyant Tools</a> to <a href="https://www.laurenceanthony.net/software/antconc/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">AntConc</a>; those tools provide interactivity that carries the user across views of statistics, query matches and texts, but tend to be limited in facilitated reproducible research and in extensibility to arbitrary corpus cleaning and analysis procedures. Tying the resources we’ve looked at to user outcomes also gives a better understanding how to evaluate accessibility of a notebook and the learning opportunities arising from it, such as to what extent a resource:</p>
<ul>
<li>supports the user getting their own data into the notebook.</li>
<li>demonstrates the combination of multiple techniques into research.</li>
<li>helps a researcher choose techniques relevant to their research question.</li>
<li>supports the user to experiment with the code of the notebook</li>
<li>demonstrates the processes and challenges around using/applying a technique and the code needed to implement those decisions e.g. decisions to make before and after applying topic models.</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, we’ve talked little about how notebooks present their content, and how that presentation might affect user engagement and the sustainability of the resource. Of course, those concerns are also important in looking at principles for quality in notebook resources for digital humanities and other text analytics users.</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>